All right, good morning everybody. Um,
thanks for being here today. Uh, Dominic
uh was not able to attend today, so me
and Jorge will be doing our darnest to
uh facilitate here. And yeah, thanks
y'all for being here.
Great. Good morning everyone. Uh thank
you for being here. Uh my name is F
Gonzalez the medical psilocybin program
manager. Uh and we have other folks here
uh from the department of health joining
us but uh Ian is the chair and Ian take
it away.
>> So good morning everyone. My name is Ian
Dunn. I'm the chair of the patient
qualification and safety committee. Um I
want to welcome you guys all here.
Anyone who decided to join. We really
appreciate your input. And uh just as a
quick reminder of what committees are,
they're a way to facilitate community
input um into the board. That way we
combine the minds of New Mexicans across
the state to make the best possible
program for New Mexicans.
On today's agenda, we are going to have
um our tier 4 not appropriate at this
time considerations, also referred to as
exclusion criteria. And if time permits,
we will go over psychiatric and
neurological considerations.
So we will begin with brief
introductions. If you would like to
participate in today's meeting,
um just give a brief introduction. You
can raise your hand on who you are, what
is your area of expertise. Maybe it's
medical, maybe it's social work, maybe
it's you know just working with um
disadvantaged persons. And whatever it
is, we would love to hear from you. We
want to know are you from New Mexico or
elsewhere? You are allowed to
participate in the committee meeting if
you are not from New Mexico. We just
want to know if you are or not. And then
do you have any other affiliations? Are
you with the American Nurses
Association, American Association of
Physicians, anything like that? Um but I
will go ahead and turn it over for
introductions.
All right. And um to introduce yourself
over mic um if you'd like to do that uh
there's a mic icon in teens up at uh the
top right portion of the screen. And if
you see that you just have to click that
um to
uh select that. Oh but first um for
raising your hand sorry that would be
the first thing. Jorge's got the slide
up there and it's just a hand icon. You
raise that and then I will allow your
mic privileges after that.
I also see in the chat um Katherine
Sanchez um is introducing herself.
Katherine Sanchez, Bureau Chief Workers
Compensation Administration, Medical
Cost Containment Bureau. Thank you.
>> Perfect. Um, since I don't see any other
hands at this time, we can go ahead and
go forward with just discussing the
exclusion criteria as they're presented.
That way, we can have more discussion. I
know some people get a little bit shy
introducing themselves. So, we will just
go ahead and look straight at what we
are going to be discussing today.
>> Okay. Ian, which uh tier four? You want
the tier 4 document open?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
Bring that up for you.
>> All right.
>> All right. Perfect. So these conditions
are tier four not appropriate at this
time. So using the clinical support
framework that we adopted um at the last
meeting, the following criteria are
recommended for placement tier 4 which
states that they're not appropriate for
participation at this time. So there are
current currently a couple of situations
which would warrant exclusion
individuals under the age of 18. At the
last meeting, we decided that there's
not currently enough clinical evidence
to support the use of psilocybin in
those under the age of 18. I do want to
remind because I did see some public
comments in regards to this um that if a
patient was going through end of life um
qualified for the program under end of
life, they actually are outside of our
clinical support tier. We deferred that
entirely to the um end of life
committee. So this would only be for the
standard um non-endof life care patients
couldn't be under the age of 18.
Second, we have pregnancy. Um unknown
risk to fetal tissues. We don't want to
cause any harm to um a developing fetus.
And three, breastfeeding unless the
patient and provider implement and
document a plan to pump and discard
breast milk for at least 24 hours
following administration. So that's just
standard protocol, just making sure that
we're not um taking, you know, the baby
on a trip. And the next section is
medications. So for all disqualifying
medications, I don't want the provider
just to say no, you take this, you're
out, done. So I included language that
said um the provider shall document a
discussion with the patient regarding
whether the benefits of tapering and
attempting psilocybin treatment outweigh
the clinical risks. So the current most
risky ones are use of lithium in the
past 30 days. This increases seizure
threshold um and can be a risk to
patients. The use of MAOIs in the past
30 days is a huge increased risk of
serotonin toxicity.
And then we have active intoxication
from alcohol or non-medinal substances
at the time of evaluation or recent
stimulant use including cocaine or
impetamines within the past 5 days due
to increased cardiovascular risk. Again,
pretty straightforward. Um,
cocaine and amphetamines both increase
your heart rate and can have increased
uh heart blood pressure. Sorry. Um, so
we don't want to add a psilocybin which
can also increase um heart rate and
blood pressure because that would put
them at a strain cardiovascular risk.
The next section is going to be
stabilization before treatment. So these
are not um full-on disqualifying. We're
not saying, you know, this ever happens,
you're out. But we do want to make sure
that we further assess them. We want to
make sure we stabilize them and and that
they're in the right state of mind for
um
psilocybin treatment. So this would
include things like an active psychotic
episode, uh clinically significant
uncontrolled hypertension, uncontrolled
diabetes malitis,
uncontrolled seizure disorder, or
current suicidal or homicidal ideiation
with intent, plan or inability to
maintain safety. All pretty standard. Um
diabetes malitis can be um can come with
electrolyte imbalances and that can
cause um that can be exacerbated by
psilocybin. So, we want to avoid that.
We definitely don't want to induce a
seizure. Um, and we definitely don't
want to put someone in a situation where
they may be a risk to themselves or
others. So, I believe those are all
pretty justified. Um, if you could
scroll down for me, Jorge.
Perfect. And then these are the hardline
conditions. So these are
contraindications to participation in
psilocybin services and are not eligible
for treatment regardless of enhanced
clinical support or specialist
consultation under tier two or three.
Reassessment may occur for medical
conditions that have demonstrabably
resolved and for which documentation
supports sustained clinical stability.
Enduring psychiatric diagnosises
associated with an elevated risk of
psychosis or media are considered
exclusionary. So, if someone has um
bipolar, but they've been stable for a
long time, they would be able to get
that reviewed. Um but if someone does
have like an active bipolar that is
coming with mania and all sorts of other
things, then we might want to um exclude
them at this time until we can get
demonstrable resolved activity for that
disorder. This also adding this resolved
documentation or resolved language
allows for let's say a patient goes to
one medical provider gets diagnosed with
bipolar and they actually had ADHD.
Well, if the second provider is able to
mark that initial condition as resolved,
this would allow them to still
participate in the program without being
overly exclusive. So these conditions
are uh schizophrenia spectrum disorders.
So schizophrenia, schizopffective
disorder and schizophrenia, schizophren
disorder. It is a history of persistent
or recurrent psychotic disorder
including psychosis precipitated by
serotonin psychedelic exposure. That is
really big words to say. If you develop
psychosis um due to taking a psychedelic
medication
um
then we should definitely not be giving
you more. Um, we just want to make sure
that you're safe in the right state of
mind and if this is going to be a
problem for you, we definitely don't
want to give you something that's going
to make you worse. I included a history
of bipolar one disorder and I think this
might be one of the more contentious
areas. There is emerging evidence that
um, bipolar 2 may be benefited by use of
psychedelics. So, I didn't want to write
it as a hardline exclusion at this time,
but I would understand if you guys
wanted to. And bipolar 2 definitely
doesn't have the same level of evidence
that the rest of the conditions do. So,
if you wanted to do it now and put
bipolar 2, we could um just recognize
that it may become a qualifying
condition in the future. So if someone
had let's say PTSD and bipolar 2, they
may be able to benefit from psychedelic
treatment, whereas someone with bipolar
one generally would be made worse.
And in terms of a history of borderline
personality disorder, this was um very
simple, very straightforward. It can c
come with rapid mood swings and rapid
cycling um which can cause problems if
we're trying to get them into an
integration therapy, have them stable
during administration and allow them a
true healing process.
Um obviously for cardiovascular issues,
severe congestive heart failure, um
active structural heart disease,
valvular disease, cardiac hypertrophy,
um
and clinically significant arhythmias as
well as cerebrovascular disease and
pulmonary disease requiring supplemental
oxygen.
Active coronary artery disease including
history of myioardial inffection. Those
are all caused because uh psychedelics
can increase your blood pressure and
strain on your cardiovascular system. So
we definitely don't want to make those
situations worse. Some other less
medical um they still are medical but
less specific diagnosis
are a known allergy to psilocybin
containing mushrooms. Obviously, not
everyone's going to know right away if
they have an allergy to psilocybin
containing mushrooms, but if we do find
out um probably shouldn't give them more
and um an active inability to provide
informed consent, I think this is very
important. A patient needs to know what
they are getting themselves into if
they're going to undergo this treatment.
Um so, if they are unable to understand
what the drug is and provide that
informed consent, I don't believe um
this is the treatment for them. But that
is all of the conditions that I have um
currently listed. So if anyone has some
other conditions that they think should
be added um I would let you raise your
hand now.
And again to raise your hand um in teams
there's a icon at the top that says
raise uh with a hand icon um if you're
able to do that. and then I can enable
your mic privileges from there.
I also did want to note I did for
totally forget to say um I was moving
things between um you know separating
out the situations from the medications
from the conditions but from what needs
to be stabilized and I guess while
moving things around I totally forgot to
include borderline personality disorder
in the version that I sent out. Um I do
want to note that it is included in this
version and then once again I'll turn it
over. Is there any conditions we think
need to be added?
All right, I'm seeing no hands. Let me
check the chat.
Don't see any hands raised or anything
in the chat so far.
>> All right. So, does anyone have any
conditions that they think we need to
strike?
You have a quiet group this morning,
Ian.
>> I do. Um well, if we do not have any
additions or striking that we need to
do, we can go ahead and have a vote on
um the adoption of this exclusion
criteria.
Uh if you can pull up the hand slide for
me.
Yes.
>> Okay. Getting there.
>> Oh, hold up. We got uh
and
and then um we got a couple of hands.
Was that for votes or for speaking? Just
want to make sure I let everyone go.
Voting. Okay, cool. Um, all right, then
we will go ahead and raise your hand now
at this time if you are in support of
the not appropriate at this time
document that I had just read up.
Okay, so far we I see four hands.
All right, with four affirmations. Do we
have any negation at this time? Please
lower your hands.
All right. And then please raise your
hand if you are in negation.
>> See no hands. Ian,
>> perfect. Four. Yes. Zero. No. This
recommendation passes, so we can go
ahead and move on to our psychiatric and
neurological considerations.
>> Okay.
>> Also, just real quick, um, for everybody
who, uh, voted, um, if you also could,
uh, if you wouldn't mind just leaving a
brief, um, uh, just introduction to
yourself in the chat as well, that would
be helpful.
>> Thank you, Johnny.
>> All right.
All right. So
I will now at this time so current
psychiatric conditions that we did not
just vote on include delusional
disorders, impaired reality testing,
dissociative disorders, delusional
disorder, dementia or moderate to severe
cognitive impairment, history of
traumatic brain injury with residual
deficits and we do good hormones.
So, does anyone have any psychiatric
conditions that you feel we missed in
that original one?
And I see a comment.
That was an introduction.
All right. And then so I will go ahead
and go through these in order. I will
open up
um discussion on delusional disorders.
So which of the four tiers and I'm going
to give you a little reminder. So tier
one is standard support um what most
patients will go through.
Tier two is enhanced clinical support.
it is basically just creating a risk
mitigation plan um for the patient but
not requiring um you know too much extra
from them. Tier three is where it gets a
little bit more barrieresque. That's
where there is two specialists that need
to sign off and then tier four is what
we just voted on not appropriate at this
time. So for delusional disorders, uh
what are we feeling?
And I see Ann's hand is up.
All right, Ann, I have enabled your mic.
Um, you can unmute whenever you're
ready.
Again, to do that, um, there's the mic
icon up at the top, uh, right of the
Teams window. Um,
if you are having issues as well, uh,
you might want to check there's a little
arrow with a drop-down
um, uh, that has speaker and microphone
settings. Um, if you want to check that
the correct microphone
is selected as well.
>> Sorry about that. I, uh, had to log back
out. Um,
>> oh, no worries. Thanks. I I guess I was
just wondering is it a history of
delusional disorders and impaired
reality testing or is it current active
delusional disorders?
>> Um so I imagined it as a history of
delusional disorder. Um
>> okay
>> so with a history of delusional disorder
I'll go ahead and write that in. Um,
what category would you put it in? I'm
kind of leaning three or two, maybe four
if we're being really strict. Um, but I
did want to hear y'all's thoughts.
>> Well, I mean, I I you know, I mean, I'll
be really transparent about this. I
mean, I I don't live in Albuquerque and
I don't live in Santa Fe and, you know,
the likelihood of being able to have a
medical provider with me during a
session to do this really is highly
unlikely. And also, I just think my
patient population would not be able to
afford that. Um, so a lot of these
conditions would be conditions I
wouldn't even consider working with
because probably I'm going to end up
working alone. Um, which is not to say I
want to make rules for the rest of the
state based on my personal
circumstances. Um, but just to kind of
offer some transparent feedback. Um, you
know, I work in Colorado
and um, you know, I would really not be
comfortable even working with somebody
with bipolar 2 on my own. So, um, yeah,
I would be really open to other people's
thoughts, but um, just recognizing the
geographic
differences in our state and also sort
of access to resources. Um, it's just
something to kind of consider that these
would be tier four for my personal
circumstances.
>> Perfect. Thank you so much for sharing.
And then I see James.
>> All right, James, I have enabled your
mic.
>> Laura and Ian in group. Um, you know, my
thoughts on this Ian are, um, definitely
uh, you know, with our risk mitigation
strategy, right? This fits right into
that category. Schizophrenia is one of
those very
history um of it fits right in here for
for psych uh psychiatric conditions and
disorders. I think for the delusional
disorder definitely we need to have
schizophrenia. Um and it I'm I'm really
torn because they definitely still need
help but this has to be a category three
to me. Um, and I'm I'm with an we need
to look at resources um and with our
provider availability and especially
with a specialist very limited and so we
need to really look at um but I I I
still think it needs to fit into a three
Ian because it's a very serious
condition that can go very south on you
if you if you don't have the stuff
ready. Even if you have it ready, it can
still be unpredictable. So to me,
schizophrenia,
um, of course, I I didn't know if that
was that also that I know we talked
about the bipolar spectrum disorders
before. Um, I I think some borderline
personality
um, fits in here as well. Um, of course,
the active hallucinations, mania, uh,
hypermania,
uh, any active delusions, paranoia would
also, uh, be somebody that would be
schizophrenic. So, I like the history of
schizophrenia versus active on this one
because most people that are
schizophrenic are active in and out. So,
um I I like more of the history thought.
Um but that's just my piece on where it
fits in a category three um versus just
excluding them completely.
Um thank you.
>> Yeah. So where I had put um history of
schizophrenia spectrum disorders in the
first document that we worked on it was
um listed as a exclusion unless they had
um documentation to show that it had
demonstrabably resolved. Um I am
definitely one that says like you know
just because you had episodes or things
in your youth doesn't mean that that's
going to carry on for you your whole
life. It also doesn't mean it's not
going to carry on for you for your whole
life. Um, so I definitely have
considered schizophrenia as like we can
maybe do it. Um, I am very uncomfortable
given the genetic predisposition to
schizophrenia. Um
typically what we see in practice is
um schizophrenia can be almost not
avoided but if we don't have a trigger
for it it can remain dormant for a long
time. And so my fear with schizophrenia
specifically was that it would be the
activating cause for those
hallucinations and for um you know their
other symptoms that they're
experiencing. Um, and I didn't want to
leech onto that. So, I had originally
put it in tier four. Um,
but for delusional disorders, are you
saying for tier three or four?
>> Uh, tier three. I like I like a good
tier three approach, Ian, on this one.
Um, for the delusional disorders, just
to see if we can give them an
opportunity, like you said, maybe
mentally, chemically they've changed,
maybe not. Uh but it it does allow at
least a reassessment, right? So that's
the kind of thought on this one is is a
reassessment. I like that idea. I like
your approach on it.
>> Yeah. Okay, perfect. That sounds good to
me. I would concur with a tier three as
well. Um does anyone have any
um I would put uh and then Ellen in the
chat said, "I agree to put history of
delusional disorders in the same place
as history of schizophrenia spectrum
since it is in the schizophrenia
spectrum." reassessment tier three. Um,
okay. So, we will put delusional
disorders in tier three. It also looks
like par postpartum psychosis or
delusional disorder might be an example
where it would be appropriate to be in
tier three. That was from Ann Mets.
So, I definitely would support that. I
think that um delusions and psychosis
both are very variable. And I think
that's why in trauma-informed speech, we
typically use like um whatever word they
use to describe them, the feelings that
they felt plus experience. Um but I do
believe that this psychedelics have an
increased risk of psychosis, especially
if they're already vulnerable to things
like that. So I would concur with a tier
three. Um what about history of impaired
reality testing?
and then Ellen.
>> All right, I have enabled your mic.
Ellen,
>> thanks. And thanks everyone. I guess for
the you know I last time we had our
meeting I had mentioned too about kind
of thinking about what we're talking
about from an assessment perspective
because I think this is an important
piece is what are we defining as a
history of impaired reality testing
because um a lot of times we will look
at something like even poor insight as
you know impaired reality testing. So,
you know, I just think that that's for
me personally, I think it's a little too
big
to even mention.
Okay. So, we have current discussion on
striking the impaired reality testing. I
would be okay with that only on the
grounds that we already said that it
would be irresponsible to um
allow someone who had was it inability
to provide informed consent. So I think
that would also fall under there to be
protected.
But if we don't like the vagueness of
this language, we could definitely
strike it. What does anyone else think?
I do appreciate your comment.
All right. And then James,
>> your mic is enabled.
>> Thank you everyone. Um and Ian, you
know, and and you know, with the
Freudian thoughts on that, um my thought
was is that we it currently we could
strike it. Um,
I just think we're still covered. I just
don't know if we need to exclude
that, especially with the cause of the
of that and and the and the the basis of
it and and what we're actually looking
at with diagnosing that. Um, I would
just strike it at this time. That's my
thought too, Leanne.
>> Perfect. I've went ahead and strike it.
if there are no other comments.
All right. Um and then the next one we
have is dissociative disorders. Uh did
dissociative amnes dissociative amnesia
and then um
other dissociative
disorders
depersonalization and derealization
disorder as well. Any
comments on dissociative disorders?
>> Looks like there's a comment in the
chat. Uh Ann wrote, "Uh, nice
improvement."
>> And then Ann also has her hand raised.
Uh, your mic is enabled.
I'm I I'm sort of curious if there's any
I mean is there anything in the
literature about dissociative disorders
benefiting from this? Um I'm just kind
of trying to imagine the rims that
they're going to have with any FDA
approval and um trying to imagine a
situation in which somebody with um with
did
eligible. It just seems really unlikely.
Um, and you know, I mean, I just for the
integrity of our program and for its
continuence um, in the future just being
far out of line with what is happening
across the nation um, feels like it
could be sort of problematic. Um, but
obviously there might be literature that
comes down the road that says that it
could be a helpful treatment. it just
sort of seems like it's um a really
significant clinical risk for anyone to
take. Um and I might put be inclined to
put it in tier four.
>> I actually wouldn't disagree with that
at all. I think um tier 4 is probably
the best place. The reason why I
included it is because um severe PTSD
can have um dissociative symptoms that
can often be um either miscatategorized
or jointly categorized as a dissociative
disorder. Um and I don't think we should
be
taking someone out of their current
headsp space if they have an inability
to stay in their current headsp space.
Not that that's a bad thing, just that I
don't want to create undue risk to the
facilitator and to any other um patients
that may be around them. So, I would
concur with tier four, but I'd love to
hear what um Alan has to say.
>> Sure.
>> Well, thanks Ian. I was going to say
something very similar in the sense of
when we see in PTSD dissociative it
really is a trauma response and it's
really a it's not the problem it's a
solution for them a lot of times for
patients so I want to be clear about
maybe is this something again that's
been in the past is this a current you
know maybe that needs to be redefined
because that was something that was with
some of the other things that we've
talked about where I don't want to
Again, I was also worried about if
someone was just dis like categorized as
a delusional disorder or put on top of a
PTSD, you know, where where that really
has been the solution for them to
disassociate and that, you know,
honestly at the end of the day, we would
hope that any kind of trauma processing,
especially done with a psychedelic,
could be actually helpful for that. So
that would be my argument is just to not
have it there at all, but maybe looking
at if there was a history of that again
in a reassessment.
>> Okay. And then James
>> can Ian also to include with with this
disassociative disorders with the DID
and the DRDP. Uh normally we also
include the de depression
depressionization and derealization
disorder. Uh that falls underneath that
dissociative disorders. I just didn't
know if we wanted to include that and
then move it to four. That's my thought.
Thank you.
>> Yeah. So I would consider DPDR um to be
with dissociative identity disorder and
dissociative amnesia um and would concur
with it being in tier 4. My problem kind
of is to concur with Ellen in that
sometimes providers instead of entering
a diagnosis for what the diagnosis is
actually supposed to be for, they enter
it to um explain symptoms. So for
instance, if someone is having PTSD but
with severe um you know dissociation,
they might enter a code of a diagnosis
to remind them when they next see the
patient that hey this person has um a
lot of dissociation symptoms. check in
on that, that kind of thing. And not
necessarily because they are actually
have a true dissociative disorder. Um,
so I would be okay with striking or
moving it to tier 4, but I do um given
there's a little bit of a mixed bag. Um,
if there's any other
comments on that would be appreciated.
All right. Um,
for now as a placeholder, we will just
keep it in tier 4.
And then so for neurological
neurological considerations, um, I
considered dementia or moderate to
severe cognitive impairment. However, I
think that um
this is
already covered on our inability to
provide informed consent. So, I would
also be um
we could either strike it or we could
keep it in tier 4. Um or I suppose put
it wherever you guys feel is best. Um
but I will open comments for dementia or
moderate to severe cognitive impairment.
Oh, and just in the chat, um, Annmet
says, "Building policy around providers
who do a lousy job of diagnosing is
problematic." And then Ellen Shiml says,
"Well, in the DSM isn't always helpful
in differentiating, so there is a lot of
clinical leeway,
especially like um something I've seen a
lot in the medical cannabis space is
marking a patient as cannabis dependent,
which doesn't mean that they have a use
disorder. It doesn't mean that they are,
you know, actively struggling with
addiction. it means they have use
cannabis and they depend on it to
relieve their symptoms. Um, so it's just
a note to the provider themselves to
say, "Hey, they use cannabis, watch out
for things like serotonin syndrome and
others." Um, but it's not necessarily
bad that they're entering things like
that. It's just another way of
note-taking um on our patients. And then
Ellen had a comment.
>> Thanks. I I agree with what you just
said too. Um, Ian, and I was just going
to say for I I hate to always be a
stickler for for semantics, but when we
talk about residual deficits, I've
worked with a lot of patients with PE or
with um TDI and I guess is we're talking
about what level of residual cognitive
deficits cuz you know there's spectrum.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I actually would agree
to just strike that entirely because we
got the informed consent part. That's
all that mattered to me in regards to
the TBI with residual deficits was are
they able to give informed consent? If
they are, great.
All right.
So, we I will go ahead and strike
dementia and um
traumatic brain injury. So, I want to
ask um is there any other psychiatric
conditions you feel like I'm missing um
that we need to add that have kind of
slipped through the cracks? I'm not
perfect. I will occasionally forget a
certain mental condition, psychiatric
condition. And um
yeah, if there's any others that you
feel that I am missing at this time.
>> Yes. In the chat, we've got from James
Brown for dissociative disorders. Can we
add um depersonalization
derealization disorder?
Yes, we can. I have just added it to the
list.
And then something I had heard um
in the written comments was about HPPPD.
Um, do we have any thoughts on that
>> James
Ian and group I have actually a lot of
thoughts on HPPPD. Um, it is something
that is very rare but it's something
that's very serious. Um it is something
that we need to have an idea that it
will occur and when it does occur what's
our action plan we need a plan around
this as a state as a group that says
when a individual does go into HPPD one
we need to educate on it we need to say
who out there is going to these
facilitators are maybe maybe you know in
a worst case scenario will see HPPD if
you do you know in that safety plan what
do you doing to help that patient? Um,
and the time and effort. So, most HPDPD
is time we say. So, more time the
better. Uh, which some people don't
have, but if you have time that it will
wear off. There's reversal drugs. We can
use two things out on the market right
now. Um, and a benzo daisopene. Um, and
I'm not saying most of these people will
have a benzo available, but if they if
they have to call emergency services, if
EM, you know, if emergency services, EMS
shows up, um, they will be able to
administer benzo um, on site and that
would typically Ian and group, you know,
reverse that HPBD uh, pretty fast,
rapidly. Um, there's also a medication
that we can use. Um, but that's more in
the actual setting of a a clinic or
emergency room would have that. Um, but
that's really I don't think it's going
to happen all the time. I don't I don't
see this occurrence um a high occurrence
of it. Again, I just see a low
occurrence of it. But with those visual
impairments and that disillusion
disorder is very serious for that
patient because they can lose time,
effort, ability to cope with that
mechanism. Um, and so I think it needs
to be addressed. I just don't know if we
need to what we need to put it in or
where we need to place it. Um, as far as
like a plan of action on it. That's why
I had
>> Yeah, I think we um definitely can not
at this time but I have been thinking
about it a lot and the place I think
would be best is in um we have
jurisdiction over like emergency
response preparedness. Um and so it
could be something as simple as like
making sure an ambulance is on call cuz
most ambulances that I've know of um
carry larazipam with them. um which
would if benzoazipines are the reversal
drug that would help with that. Um
so I think we could definitely it should
be in two places. One should be in
education to facilitators so that they
know what's going on and just not
shocked if they ever see it. um and to
make sure that you know if we are
administering this that there's adequate
access to you know whether it's an
ambulance whether it's whatever to en
ensure that they can get um the
medications they need. One of the more
frustrating parts about um federal
regulation is benzo, the primary not
reversal but stabilization agent for
psychedelics typically
or not typically it is a controlled
substance and we would not have DEA
authorization to hold it. Um, but we
definitely could have an ambulance
nearby that would have lorazzipm and
could administer that with while being
on a different site and not directly
regulated by the DEA. Um, but I do think
that is a really important point. um
almost like how
not quite the same but similar vibe as
we didn't provide a lot of education to
providers on um
canabonoid hypermmesis syndrome and then
providers didn't know how to deal with
it and now in um nursing school we are
taught about canabonoid hyperammesis
syndrome um to help prevent some of the
problems from coming out. Now, just like
uh what you talked about, it's a rare
condition and it's not going to affect
everyone, but um it is definitely
helpful to prepare for it. So, I do
appreciate your input.
>> Oh, and Mets put in the chat uh maybe
add to the informed consent protocol.
>> Perfect. So um the informed consent
protocol
belongs to the dosage administration
clinical practice committee but we are
definitely working on preparation
sessions at our next meeting. Um and so
we will be able to
um get those preparations that informed
consent protocol um what we need to
screen for. The thing I'm trying to
we're trying to get through today is
saying which of the tiers
do things fall into. Um because without
that they're not going to know what we
need to screen for in preparation.
Um
so
do we want to include active eating
disorders or malnutrition?
Oh, I see James has his hand up. you can
disregard my question. What did you have
to say?
>> Ian, one thought just real quick on the
HPDB to close it out. You know, there's
a great resource in the state with the
poison control center. You know, I just
wanted to bring that back up again as as
you know, that's a simple dial the phone
number 1 8002222
and then next thing you know there's
that poison control specialist on the
line and if we can teach them what HPPPD
is, you know, they might be able to
field some of those initial responses. I
don't know, it's just a thought because
it is a great resource
um and they they could field something
like HPPPD. It's not technically
anything that we take in excess is
considered a poison technically in the
body. Anything can be a poison. Water
can be a poison. Um and so HPPPD might
just fall under something where they
might want to research that data and
puts us in a data aggregation area as
well. Um just a thought on using the
state that's already set up something
there that we might be able to
capitalize on. uh you know in that
education piece to tell facilitators to
tell clinics to tell you know centers or
you know whatever we're going to call
them to say you know if you have help
call you can also call this number
besides calling EMS but just a thought
thank you
>> yeah that's actually great I really love
that idea especially because the
propagation recommendations that we just
sent require the poison control number
to already be on there so if we just
incorporate that into our you know
emergency protocols that would work out
really great um since we've already kind
of began to build a structure to um
utilize that assistance that the state
provides. I think that would be um a
very good thing. I will definitely note
that for the dosage.
All right. Um so what did we think about
active eating disorders or significant
malnutrition?
So personally I would put active eating
disorders or significant malnutrition in
um
tier two um given that you know if they
are significantly malnourished and that
leads to electrolyte abnormalities that
could be exacerbated by psilocybin. I
don't think it's a great enough risk
where we need to like specialize it out
and require all these extra barriers,
but something as simple as like a
clinical support plan and um risk
mitigation might be good for them.
Ian, I forgot to ask. Would would you
like me to in the chat put the the the
four different tiers in the chat so that
people can refer back to them?
>> Yes, please. All right.
>> Um, in response to uh what N just said,
Ellen says, I think that's fair. Then
James Brown put tier two.
>> All right.
because I think we've covered most of
the like main psychiatric bases, you
know, bipolar one, self-injurous and
self harm behavior. Um,
uh, impaired cognitive impairment via
the informed consent. Um,
seizure disorders that are partially
controlled. We got um delusional
dissociative
personality disorders. we've considered
and
the main two medications that we've
considered. So, does anyone have any
even non psychiatric conditions that
they think we've missed at this point?
And then for the bipolar two, um
tier three or do you guys want to until
we get enough evidence
just tier for it?
All
right, James has his hand up. Uh, your
mic is enabled.
>> And, you know, going back to risk
versus, uh, you know, on the facilitator
or center and the patient's risk, it
definitely sits in three. Um, I just
don't want to exclude these people. Um
the data behind bipolar disorders and
research
shows a mixed bag. Um definitely they've
said hey schizophrenia, lithium, maybe
even things like clausipine, you know,
those things are out the door. Um but
bipolar disorder, it doesn't necessarily
mean that the patient should not be able
to receive services to me. Um but I
definitely think there needs to be a
safety um behind it. And so three fits
that category.
um without excluding them at this time,
you know, until we have more data or
more research. That's my thought.
>> Yeah. And I completely agree. I actually
um
there can be overlapping conditions. I
think we're aware. So just because you
know someone has bipolar 2 disorder,
that might not be their primary um
concern. It could be the nightmares
associated with PTSD. It could be the
anxiety. So, um I definitely agree with
uh you James and Ellen who uh said I
would agree with tier three and bipolar
2 in the chat. So, I will go ahead and
enter that.
>> Looks like
her hand raised. Um, Ellen, your mic is
enabled.
>> Oh, sorry if I missed this because I
don't think I was as paying attention to
the tears either or I was thinking that
floor was a little different. So, when
we talk about dissociative personality
and dissociative disorders um I mean I
that was I thought there was a little
conversation about that as far as from a
personality disorder.
Yes. You know, I I understand that's
ingrained and if we're putting that as a
tier four, but dissociative identity
disorder and dissociative disorders are
not considered personality disorders.
And I don't know that that's where I was
saying with the history or if someone
had maybe that put down somewhere along
with a PTSD or something else
potentially that I didn't want to
completely disclude some of those
people. if they had like episodes of
derealization or depersonalization,
that's not uncommon that it might be a
PTSD that they got that diagnosis on top
of it and it's actually coming from
trauma. So, I was a little concerned
about having that completely as a tier
4. Now, something like a personality
disorder, that's a little different. Um,
but to me, not not the dissociative
disorder, that's not considered a
personality disorder. I would still
argue that that should be considered
under tier three especially with a
history of things.
>> Perfect. All right. Thank you. Um so do
we are we in agreement that dissociative
disorder should be in tier three or do
we should we put them in tier four?
Uh, Ann,
>> sure. I mean I I think if there are
medical providers out there that feel
comfortable with that kind of a risk
profile, I think
um the you know overlap of symptoms
between dissociative disorders and PTSD
is
uh is is is a reason to probably include
them. Um
but um yeah, I mean I think it's really
I think I think that's going to be the
you know the big issue is are providers
going to be comfortable working with
that population? Are they going to be
able to have appropriate supportive
resources? And if that's there, I think
tier three makes sense. Um yeah,
>> I I agree. I think tier three looks like
it's more exclusionary, but I think it
allows us to incorporate or to allow
more patients than otherwise would have
been allowed because I feel a doctor,
we'll say a generalist doctor um is
probably not going to feel as
comfortable treating someone with
complex um psychiatric diagnosis. But if
you got a psychiatrist on board, then
they would work together to create, you
know, that risk mitigation
um and all the tier 2 documentation, but
they would also, you know, consult them
and say, "Hey, is this right? Does this
patient fit for this?" And it defers to
someone whose only specialty is um
psychiatry. And that would if I were in
that position and I was the prescribing
psilocybin practitioner, I would feel
much more confident if I got a complex
case and someone reviewed it with me
than if I was doing it alone. So I would
agree with dissociative disorders in
tier three.
Um
then
I also I know this is not a psychiatric
condition but I just realized I also
omitted from the draft um
cardiovascular
accident or TAS.
Uh, where would you guys like to put Oh,
this
All right, James Brown has a stand up.
Uh, James, your mic is enabled.
A& group, you know, if that patient has
an active TIA or had a a recent TIA, you
know, that's almost a contra indication
uh for use at that point in time. So, I
didn't know if it falls underneath, you
know, kind of like with active angina or
other things of that cardiovascular.
It kind of to me fits right there with,
you know, uncontrolled hypertension and
uncontrolled things, but TI is pretty
serious.
>> I guess my question is, um, how long
would someone have to go without a CVA
or a TIA
to
be fine?
Is there any amount of time that you
think we feel would make it safe or is
>> I think there could be a
there definitely be reassessment. I
think neurologically they'd have to be
cleared by you know uh definitely their
provider would have to clear them like
they'd almost need like a even for the
facilitator and all them they'd have to
almost have like a pre-clear because it
could be forever. just depends on you
know was there a shift or no shift was
you know what's going on with the actual
you know disease state itself it could
it could limit them or prevent them
completely
>> okay I would be perfectly okay with
putting it in tier four conditions that
if they because in that definition right
it provides that um
re reassessment may occur only for
medical conditions that have demonstr
ably result and for which documentation
supports sustained clinical stability.
Um so I think that would fit in
perfectly with the other ones in that um
those other cardiovascular conditions.
All right.
So
here is what we have been working on. I
will give us anyone any time to consider
any conditions that I have not
and we can go ahead and vote on these
ones. Uh Jorge, would you mind bringing
up the document the clinical support
considerations?
You have it up. That was my bad.
So, just to recap what we've been
discussing, uh, TAS and CVAS, tier four,
active eating disorders or significant
malnutrition, tier two, bipolar 2
disorder, tier three, history of
delusional disorders, tier three,
dissociative disorders, tier three,
All right. Any comments before we move
to a vote.
All right. With no comments, we will go
ahead and vote on this. If you are um in
approval of the clinical support
considerations
that and their placements,
please raise your hand at this time.
Okay, I did see four hands.
Perfect. And then if you are against
this document, please raise your hand at
this time. Or sorry, lower your hands
first.
And then
if you are in against this document,
please raise your hand at this time.
And then the clinical support
considerations are considered.
All righty. Well, that is what I had to
go over today. Um, so
see if I have
all right. Well, I don't have anything
else prepared for today. Does anyone
else have any comments, things we should
discuss at the next meeting um or things
like that?
I just want to remind folks uh
on the screen we had how to submit uh
written public comment. Um do the
document if you submit a document no
more than three three pages in length
10point font uh please include your full
legal name and any organizational
affiliations and please send those to
the medical.silocybin
doh.nm.gov
uh email by 5:00 the next day 5:00 p.m.
the next day.
>> All righty. So now is the most fun part
of the meeting. we get to decide our
next meeting date.
So, let's see here.
All right. And then this one should have
all of the Yeah. Okay, cool. All right.
So,
looks like
the dosage committee will meet on the
16th. They will be working on
preparation session stuff. Would
everyone be free for the 17th at 9
or do you all have a date that works
better?
>> The 17th is going to be a Tuesday.
>> That looks good for us so far as well.
>> Anyone in the chat not able to make it
that day? I saw a couple of thumbs up
go. Cool.
Well, then we will do the 17th at
9:00 a.m.
>> Great.
>> I will call this meeting adjourned.
Thank you guys so much for coming. I
appreciate all of your input, all of the
time that you guys put in today, and all
of the debate. Um, I really appreciate
all of you guys just taking the time to
be here. It means more to me than you
guys know. Um, and I'm really glad that
we're going to make a great program
together. So again, thank you and have a
great rest of your week.
>> Thank you everyone. Thanks for being
here.